A Guide to the Sara Clarke Lippincott/Grace Greenwood Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7081-d
Sara Clarke Lippincott/Grace Greenwood Collection 1844-1903
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7081-d
28 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, 1971 January 21
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - "Effie Mather A tale of New England" by Grace Greenwood, AMsS, 8 p.
    [Incomplete: pages numbered 1 -4 and 17 -20.]
  - "Reminiscences of Washington Before & During the War" by Grace Greenwood, 1892 December; AMsS, 11 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Says Juliet, in her balcony,..." signed Grace Greenwood, [1893 Aug 16]; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Sweet Juliet in her balcony...", 1859 Mar 1; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "To George Peabody" by [ Grace Greenwood], n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
- Letters
  - Sara J[ane] Clarke[ Grace Greenwood], Warren, Ohio, to Sally Holley, Rochester, New York, 1844 June 2; ALS, 1 p.
    [Letter of introduction for Mr. Wills of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, "a Liberty Abolitionist, and with the ardent devotion of a pilgrim..." who will "attend the convention for the erection of the monument to the memory of your lamented father --" [ Myron Holley(1779-1841)]. Praises Wills as a "champion of Freedom."]
  - Grace Greenwood, Washington, to [Edwin Percy] Whipple(1819-1886), 1852 Apr 16; ALS, 1 p.
    [Letter of introduction for W[illiam] T[urner] Coggeshall(1824-1867) of Cincinnati, Ohio, also of the press.]
  - Grace Greenwood, Blackhearth Park, to [George] Virtue(ca. 1793-1868), 1852 Oct 18; ALS, 3 p.
    [Thanks him for the offer to bring out one of her juvenile books. Regrets not being able to write a preface because of illness and going to Paris, France. Requests that his proposed alterations to the language be given to [Francis] Bennoch(1812-1890) for approval. Comments that
    Heads and Tails; Studies and Stories of Pets
    would be a better book to begin with rather than
    Recollections of My Childhood, and Other Stories
    . ]
  - Grace Greenwood, Cleveland, Ohio, to [Anne Lynch] Botta(1815-1891), 1855 Jul 17; ALS, 3 p.
    [Letter of introduction for Virginia Wagner, a French-German lady, who wishes to establish herself in this country as a teacher.]
  - Grace Greenwood, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to C[ ] K[ ] Gallup, 1862 Nov 14; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends an autograph.]
  - Grace Greenwood, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to [ ] Porter, 1868 Oct 25; ALS, 4 p.
    [Reminds him of their meeting years ago before asking for a favor; mentions Fanny Fern(1811-1872); comments on wanting to write for the
    New York Ledger
    in addition to the
    Independent
    and certain magazines; mentions [Robert] Bonner(1824-1899) in reference to this matter; comments that she wants "to arrive at something like a certainty in regard to my literary work for the coming season --"]
  - Grace [Greenwood], Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to "My dear friend", 1869 Jan 22; ALS, 4 p.
    [Relates the importance of their constant friendship. Thanks the recipient for his book and comments on "Lines on a Tea Leaf," a portrait of herself, as being perhaps a little overdrawn. Tries to persuade the recipient to visit Washington, D. C. to regain strength and courage. Mentions her mother's visit and her attendance of the sessions of the "Colored Men's Convention and the Woman's Suffrage Convention," and going to hear Fred[erick] Douglas(1817-1895). Mentions her own "Yankee Sketches" in the
  - Grace Greenwood, Washington, D. C., to "Dear Rebecca", 1876 Nov 26; ALS, 4 p.
    [Discusses her illness of the past few weeks. Sends one of [Charles] Dickens' (1812-1870) notes and comments that she has mislaid Jean Ingelow's (1820-1897) autograph.]
  - Grace Greenwood, Washington, D. C., to "My dear child", 1877 Mar 24; ALS, 1 p.
  - Grace Greenwood, New York, New York, to [Oliver] Johnson(1809-1889), 1881 May 14; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests assistance in retrieving a copy of her sketch of [ Joseph Massini] from the
    New York Tribune
    and send it to her in care of Mrs. Vincenzo [ Anne Lynch] Botta. ]
  - Grace Greenwood to [ Edward W.] Bok(1863-1930), 1887 Dec 5; ALS, 3 p.
    [Thanks him for the kind words and deeds, including the Jenny Lind(1820-1897) letter. Sends regards to [ Sarah Tittle Barrett] Bolton(1814-1893). Asks to borrow a copy of
    The Century
  - S[ara] J[ane] Lippincott[ Grace Greenwood], [on letterhead "Shawme Farm, Sandwich, Mass."], to Charles Elmer Rice, Mount Union, Stark County, Ohio, 1890 Jul 10; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Promises to find some autographs, including a Fanny Fern letter, upon her return to her New York home; mentions Margaret Bailey, Marcellus Reily, Lydia Maria Child(1802-1880), Lucy Stone Blackwell(1818-1893), Elizabeth [Palmer] Peabody(1804-1894), and William Lloyd Garrison(1805-1879).]
  - Grace Greenwood, [New York, New York], to [William Hayes] Ward(1835-1916), 1890 Nov 20; ALS, 3 p.
    [Concerns literary matters, including publishing pieces from her Washington "Recollections."]
  - Grace Greenwood, Washington, D. C., to [Henry Chandler] Bowen(1813-1896), 1893 Apr 18; ALS, 4 p.
    [Concerns her Washington "Reminiscences" and the method of its publication; mentions [William Hayes] Ward. ]
  - Grace Greenwood, Washington, D. C., to "Dear old Chappie", 1894 May 23; ALS, 4 p.
    [Mentions the prose of Charles [Warren] Stoddard(1843-1899) and the death of the Marchese [Della Fonte Filippo] Biscaccianti. ]
  - Grace Greenwood' ("Mrs. S. J. Lippincott"), Washington, D. C., to Gilson Willets(1869- ), 1897 Aug 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Regrets that she is unable to assist him with his article (on herself); mentions her homes in Washington, D. C. and New Brighton, Pennsylvania and her grandson Herbert Lippincott Winslow and her son-in-law Herbert Hall Winslow. ]
  - Grace Greenwood, Washington, D. C., to Gilson Willets, 1897 Nov 28; ALS, 3 p.
    [Concerns his article on Greenwood, offering assistance, some photographs and biographical sketches; mentions an oil painting by George P[eter Alexander] Healy(1813-1894).]
  - S[ara] J[ane] Lippincott[ Grace Greenwood], Washington, D. C., to Gilson Willets, 1897 Dec 10; ALS, 2 p.
    [Curt letter concerning his last letter which did not answer her questions; mentions being involved in duties connected with the illness, death and burial of a dear friend]
  - Sara J[ane] Lippincott[ Grace Greenwood], Washington, D. C., to Gilson Willets, 1897 Dec 11; ALS, 3 p.
    [Explains what she has done and proposes to do to further his wishes and what her wishes were concerning the article; mentions the photographs and biographical sketches.]
  - Grace Greenwood, New Rochelle, New York, to "My dear friend", 1903 Aug 12; ALS, 4 p.
    [Wishes to hear from her friend, mentioning the recipient's recent trip to England; mentions worries over domestic and business affairs; refers to [Henry] Holt(1840-1926) of the
    and her last batch of "Reminiscences" being mislaid; mentions a letter of hers printed in 1859 located by [William Hayes] Ward. ]
  - Grace Greenwood, New Rochelle, New York, to [Henry] Holt, 1903 Dec 8; ANS, 2 p.
    [Requests the next to the last manuscript of the reminiscent article be returned.]
  - Grace Greenwood to [ ] Tyler, Monday evening; ALS, 1 p.
    [Concerns letters she has prepared for him.]
  - Sara J[ane] Lippincott[ Grace Greenwood] to [Rufus Wilmot] Griswold(1815-1857), n.d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Concerns the poems she is sending to him; asks if he wants any biographical notes; requests correspondence to be sent in care of L[ouis] A[ntoine] Godey(1804-1878).]